<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" []>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="no" ?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-ietf-homenet-babel-profile-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
<front>
<title abbrev="Homenet Babel profile">Homenet profile of the Babel routing protocol</title>
<author fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek" initials="J." surname="Chroboczek">
<organization>IRIF, University of Paris-Diderot</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Case 7014</street>
<city>75205 Paris Cedex 13</city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country>France</country>
</postal>
<email>jch@pps.univ-paris-diderot.fr</email>
</address>
</author>

<date day="8" month="July" year="2016"/>

<abstract>
<t>This document defines the subset of the Babel routing protocol
<xref target="RFC6126"/> and its extensions that a Homenet router must
implement.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction">

<t>The core of the Homenet protocol suite consists of HNCP 
<xref target="RFC7788"/>, a protocol used for flooding configuration
information and assigning prefixes to links, combined with the Babel
routing protocol <xref target="RFC6126"/>.  Babel is an extensible,
flexible and modular protocol: minimal implementations of Babel have been
demonstrated that consist of a few hundred of lines of code, while the
"large" implementation includes support for a number of extensions and
consists of over ten thousand lines of C code.</t>

<t>This document defines the exact subset of the Babel protocol and its
extensions that is required by a conformant implementation of the Homenet
protocol suite.</t>

<section title="Background">

<t>The Babel routing protocol and its extensions are defined in a number
of documents:
<list style="symbols">
<t>The body of RFC&nbsp;6126 <xref target="RFC6126"/> defines the core,
unextended protocol.  It allows Babel's control data to be carried over
either link-local IPv6 or IPv4, and in either case allows announcing both
IPv4 and IPv6 routes.  It leaves link cost estimation, metric computation
and route selection to the implementation.  Distinct implementations of
core RFC&nbsp;6126 Babel will interoperate and maintain a set of loop-free
forwarding paths, but given conflicting metrics or route selection
policies may give rise to persistent oscillations.</t>
<t>The informative Appendix&nbsp;A of RFC&nbsp;6126 suggests a simple and
easy to implement algorithm for cost and metric computation that has been
found to work satisfactorily in a wide range of topologies.</t>
<t>While RFC&nbsp;6126 does not provide an algorithm for route selection,
its Section&nbsp;3.6 suggests selecting the route with smallest metric
with some hysteresis applied.  An algorithm that has been found to work
well in practice is described in Section&nbsp;III.E of
<xref target="DELAY-BASED"/>.</t>
<t>The extension mechanism for Babel is defined in RFC&nbsp;7557 <xref
target="RFC7557"/>.</t>
<t>Four RFCs and Internet-Drafts define optional extensions to Babel:
HMAC-based authentication <xref target="RFC7298"/>, source-specific
routing <xref target="BABEL-SS"/>, radio interference aware routing <xref
target="BABEL-Z"/>, and delay-based routing <xref target="BABEL-RTT"/>.
All of these extensions interoperate with the core protocol as well as
with each other.</t>
</list>
</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="The Homenet profile of Babel">

<section title="Requirements">

<t><list style="empty"><t>[Sentences within square brackets are editorial
notes and are not intended for publication.]</t></list></t>

<t>REQ1: a Homenet implementation of Babel MUST encapsulate Babel control
traffic in IPv6 packets sent to the IANA-assigned port 6696 and either the
IANA-assigned multicast group ff02::1:6 or to a link-local unicast
address.</t>

<t><list style="empty"><t>Rationale: since Babel is able to carry both
IPv4 and IPv6 routes over either IPv4 or IPv6, choosing the protocol used
for carrying control traffic is a matter of preference.  Since IPv6 has
some features that make implementations somewhat simpler and more reliable
(notably link-local addresses), we require carrying control data over
IPv6.</t></list></t>

<t>REQ2: a Homenet implementation of Babel MUST implement the IPv6 subset
of the protocol defined in the body of RFC&nbsp;6126.</t>

<t><list style="empty"><t>Rationale: support for IPv6 routing is an
essential component of the Homenet architecture.</t></list></t>

<t>REQ3: a Homenet implementation of Babel SHOULD implement the IPv4
subset of the protocol defined in the body of RFC&nbsp;6126.  Use of other
techniques for acquiring IPv4 connectivity (such as multiple layers of
NAT) is strongly discouraged.</t>

<t><list style="empty"><t>Rationale: support for IPv4 will remain
necessary for years to come, and even in pure IPv6 deployments, including
code for supporting IPv4 has very little cost.  Since HNCP makes it easy
to assign distinct IPv4 prefixes to the links in a network, it is not
necessary to resort to multiple layers of NAT, with all of its
problems.</t></list></t>

<t><list style="empty"><t>[BS suggest that this should be
a MUST.]</t></list></t>

<t>REQ4: a Homenet implementation of Babel MUST implement source-specific
routing for IPv6, as defined in draft-boutier-babel-source-specific <xref
target="BABEL-SS"/>.  This implies that it MUST implement the extension
mechanism defined in RFC&nbsp;7557.</t>

<t><list style="empty"><t>Rationale: source-specific routing is an
essential component of the Homenet architecture.  The extension mechanism
is required by source-specific routing.  Source-specific routing for IPv4
is not required, since HNCP arranges things so that a single non-specific
IPv4 default route is announced (Section&nbsp;6.5 of <xref
target="RFC7788"/>).</t></list></t>

<t>REQ5: a Homenet implementation of Babel MUST implement HMAC-based
authentication, as defined in RFC&nbsp;7298, MUST implement the two
mandatory-to-implement algorithms defined in RFC&nbsp;7298, and MUST
enable and require authentication when instructed to do so by HNCP.</t>

<t><list style="empty"><t>Rationale: some home networks include "guest"
links that can be used by third parties that are not necessarily fully
trusted.  In such networks, it is essential that either the routing
protocol is secured or the guest links are carefully firewalled.</t>

<t>Generic mechanisms such as DTLS and dynamically keyed IPsec are not
able to protect multicast traffic, and are therefore difficult to use with
Babel.  Statically keyed IPsec, perhaps with keys rotated by HNCP, is
vulnerable to replay attacks and would therefore require the addition of
a nonce mechanism to Babel.</t></list></t>

<t><list style="empty">
<t>[There is no consensus about this requirement.  A simpler solution is
to disable Babel on guest interfaces.  MS suggests this might be
a SHOULD.]</t>

<t>[This needs expanding with an explanation of how HNCP is supposed to
signal the use of authentication.]</t></list></t>

<t>REQ6: a Homenet implementation of Babel MUST use metrics that are of
a similar magnitude to the values suggested in Appendix&nbsp;A of
RFC&nbsp;6126.  In particular, it SHOULD assign costs that are no less
than 256 to wireless links, and SHOULD assign costs between 32 and 196 to
lossless wired links.</t>

<t><list style="empty"><t>Rationale: if two implementations of Babel
choose very different values for link costs, combining routers from
different vendors will lead to sub-optimal routing.</t></list></t>

<t>REQ7: a Homenet implementation of Babel SHOULD distinguish between
wired and wireless links; if it is unable to determine whether a link is
wired or wireless, it SHOULD make the worst-case hypothesis that the link
is wireless.  It SHOULD dynamically probe the quality of wireless links
and derive a suitable metric from its quality estimation.  The algorithm
described in Appendix&nbsp;A of RFC&nbsp;6126 MAY be used.</t>

<t><list style="empty"><t>Rationale: support for wireless transit links is
a "killer feature" of Homenet, something that is requested by our users
and easy to explain to our bosses.  In the absence of dynamically computed
metrics, the routing protocol attempts to minimise the number of links
crossed by a route, and therefore prefers long, lossy links to shorter,
lossless ones.  In wireless networks, "hop-count routing is worst-path
routing".</t>

<t>[This should probably be MUST, but it might be difficult or even
impossible to implement in some environments, especially in the presence
of wired-to-wireless bridges.]</t></list></t>

</section>

<section title="Non-requirements">

<t>NR1: a Homenet implementation of Babel MAY perform route selection by
applying hysteresis to route metrics, as suggested in Section&nbsp;3.6 of
RFC&nbsp;6126 and described in detail in Section&nbsp;III.E of
<xref target="BABEL-RTT"/>.  However, it MAY simply pick the route with
the smallest metric.</t>

<t><list style="empty"><t>Rationale: hysteresis is only useful in
congested and highly dynamic networks.  In a typical home network, stable
and uncongested, the feedback loop that hysteresis compensates for does
not occur.</t></list></t>

<t>NR2: a Homenet implementation of Babel MAY include support for other
extensions to the protocol, as long as they are known to interoperate with
both the core protocol and source-specific routing.</t>

<t><list style="empty"><t>Rationale: delay-based routing is useful in
redundant meshes of tunnels, which do not occur in typical home networks
(which typically use at most one VPN link).  Interference-aware routing,
on the other hand, is likely to be useful in home networks, but the
extension requires further evaluation before it can be recommended for
widespread deployment.</t></list></t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">

</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor="RFC6126"><front>
<title>The Babel Routing Protocol</title>
<author fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek" initials="J." surname="Chroboczek"/>
<date month="February" year="2011"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6126"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC7298'><front>
<title>Babel Hashed Message Authentication Code (HMAC) Cryptographic Authentication</title>
<author initials='D.' surname='Ovsienko' fullname='D. Ovsienko'></author>
<date year='2014' month='July' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='RFC' value='7298' />
</reference>

<reference anchor='RFC7557'><front>
<title>Extension Mechanism for the Babel Routing Protocol</title>
<author fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek" initials="J." surname="Chroboczek"/>
<date day="28" month="May" year="2015"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7557"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="BABEL-SS">
<front>
<title>Source-Specific Routing in Babel</title>
<author initials='M' surname='Boutier' fullname='Matthieu Boutier'></author>
<author initials='J' surname='Chroboczek' fullname='Juliusz Chroboczek'></author>
<date month='January' day='5' year='2015' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-boutier-babel-source-specific-01' />
</reference>

</references>

<references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor="BABEL-RTT">
<front>
<title>Delay-based Metric Extension for the Babel Routing Protocol</title>
<author initials='B' surname='Jonglez' fullname='Baptiste Jonglez'></author>
<author initials='J' surname='Chroboczek' fullname='Juliusz Chroboczek'></author>
<date month='May' day='27' year='2015' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-jonglez-babel-rtt-extension-01' />
</reference>

<reference anchor="BABEL-Z"><front>
<title>Diversity Routing for the Babel Routing Protocol</title>
<author initials='J' surname='Chroboczek' fullname='Juliusz Chroboczek'></author>
<date month='February' day='15' year='2016' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft' value='draft-chroboczek-babel-diversity-routing-01'/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC7788" target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7788">
<front>
<title>Home Networking Control Protocol</title>
<author initials="M." surname="Stenberg" fullname="M. Stenberg">
<organization/>
</author>
<author initials="S." surname="Barth" fullname="S. Barth">
<organization/>
</author>
<author initials="P." surname="Pfister" fullname="P. Pfister">
<organization/>
</author>
<date year="2016" month="April"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7788"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7788"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="DELAY-BASED"><front>
<title>A delay-based routing metric</title>
<author fullname="Baptiste Jonglez" initials="B." surname="Jonglez"/>
<author fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek" initials="J." surname="Chroboczek"/>
<date month="March" year="2014"/>
</front>
<annotation>Available online from http://arxiv.org/abs/1403.3488</annotation>
</reference>

</references>

</back>

</rfc>
