<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" []>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-babel-source-specific-07" ipr="trust200902">
<front>
<title>Source-Specific Routing in Babel</title>
<author fullname="Matthieu Boutier" initials="M." surname="Boutier">
<organization>IRIF, University of Paris-Diderot</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Case 7014</street>
<city>75205 Paris Cedex 13</city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country>France</country>
</postal>
<email>boutier@irif.fr</email>
</address>
</author>
<author fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek" initials="J." surname="Chroboczek">
<organization>IRIF, University of Paris-Diderot</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>Case 7014</street>
<city>75205 Paris Cedex 13</city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country>France</country>
</postal>
<email>jch@irif.fr</email>
</address>
</author>

<date day="28" month="October" year="2020"/>

<abstract>
<t>Source-specific routing (also known as Source-Address Dependent
Routing, SADR) is an extension to traditional next-hop routing where
packets are forwarded according to both their destination and their source
address.  This document describes an extension for source-specific routing
to the Babel routing protocol.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section title="Introduction and background">

<t>The Babel routing protocol <xref target="RFC8966"/> is a distance vector
routing protocol for next-hop routing.  In next-hop routing, each node
maintains a forwarding table which maps destination prefixes to next hops.
The forwarding decision is a per-packet operation which depends on the
destination address of the packets and on the entries of the forwarding
table.  When a packet is about to be routed, its destination address is
compared to the prefixes of the routing table: the entry with the most
specific prefix containing the destination address of the packet is
chosen, and the packet is forwarded to the associated next-hop.  Next-hop
routing is a simple, well understood paradigm that works satisfactorily in
a large number of cases.</t>

<t>Source-specific routing <xref target="SS-ROUTING"/>, or Source Address
Dependent Routing (SADR), is a modest extension to next-hop routing where
the forwarding decision depends not only on the destination address but
also on the source address of the packet being routed, which makes it
possible for two packets with the same destination but different source
addresses to be routed following different paths.  The forwarding tables
are extended to map pairs of prefixes (destination, source) to next hops.
When multiple entries match a given packet, the one with the most specific
destination prefix is chosen, and, in the case of equally specific
destination prefixes, the one with the most specific source prefix.</t>

<t>The main application of source-specific routing is a form of
multihoming known as multihoming with multiple addresses.  When using this
technique in a network connected to multiple providers, every host is
assigned multiple addresses, one per provider.  When a host sources
a packet, it picks one of its addresses as the source address, and
source-specific routing is used to route the packet to an edge router that
is connected to the corresponding provider, which is compatible with <xref
target="BCP84"/>.  Unlike classical multihoming, this technique is
applicable to small networks, as it does not require the use of
provider-independent addresses, or cause excessive growth of the global
routing table.  More details are given in <xref target="SS-ROUTING"/>.</t>

<t>This document describes a source-specific routing extension for the
Babel routing protocol <xref target="RFC8966"/>.  This involves minor
changes to the data structures, which must include a source prefix in
addition to the destination prefix already present, and some changes to
the Update, Route Request and Seqno Request TLVs, which are extended with
a source prefix.  The source prefix is encoded using a mandatory sub-TLV
(<xref target="RFC8966"/> Section 4.4).</t>

</section>

<section title="Specification of Requirements">

<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
"OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and
only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

</section>

<section title="Data Structures">

<t>A number of the conceptual data structures described in Section 3.2 of
<xref target="RFC8966"/> contain a destination prefix.  This specification
extends these data structures with a source prefix.  Data from the
original protocol, which do not specify a source prefix, are stored with
a zero length source prefix, which matches exactly the same set of packets
as the original, non-source-specific data.</t>

<section title="The Source Table">

<t>Every Babel node maintains a source table, as described in <xref
target="RFC8966"/> Section&nbsp;3.2.5.  A source-specific Babel node
extends this table with the following field:</t>
<t><list style="symbols">
<t>The source prefix specifying the source address of packets to which
this entry applies.</t>
</list></t>

<t>The source table is now indexed by triples of the form (prefix, source
prefix, router-id).</t>

<t>Note that the route entry contains a source (see sections 2 and 3.2.5 of
<xref target="RFC8966"/>) which itself contains a source prefix.  These are two
very different concepts that should not be confused.</t>

</section>

<section title="The Route Table">

<t>Every Babel node maintains a route table, as described in <xref
target="RFC8966"/> Section&nbsp;3.2.6.  Each route table entry contains,
among other data, a source, which this specification extends with a source
prefix as described above.  The route table is now indexed by triples of
the form (prefix, source prefix, neighbour), where the prefix and source
prefix are obtained from the source.</t>

</section>

<section title="The Table of Pending Seqno Requests">

<t>Every Babel node maintains a table of pending seqno requests, as
described in <xref target="RFC8966"/>, Section&nbsp;3.2.7.  A
source-specific Babel node extends this table with the following entry:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
<t>The source prefix being requested.</t>
</list></t>

<t>The table of pending seqno requests is now indexed by triples of the
form (prefix, source prefix, router-id).</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="Data Forwarding">

<t>In next-hop routing, if two routing table entries overlap, then one is
necessarily more specific than the other; the "longest prefix rule"
specifies that the most specific applicable routing table entry is
chosen.</t>

<t>With source-specific routing, there might no longer be a most specific
applicable entry: two routing table entries might match a given packet
without one necessarily being more specific than the other.  Consider for
example the following routing table:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
          destination                source     next-hop
    2001:db8:0:1::/64                  ::/0            A
                 ::/0     2001:db8:0:2::/64            B
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>This specifies that all packets with destination in 2001:db8:0:1::/64
are to be routed through A, while all packets with source in
2001:db8:0:2::/64 are to be routed through B.  A packet with source
2001:db8:0:2::42 and destination 2001:db8:0:1::57 matches both entries,
although neither is more specific than the other.  A choice is necessary,
and unless the choice being made is the same on all routers in a routing
domain, persistent routing loops may occur.  More details are
given in Section IV.C of <xref target="SS-ROUTING"/>.</t>

<t>A Babel implementation MUST choose routing table entries by using the
so-called destination-first ordering, where a routing table entry R1 is
preferred to a routing table entry R2 when either R1's destination prefix
is more specific than R2's, or the destination prefixes are equal and R1's
source prefix is more specific than R2's.  (In other words, routing table
entries are compared using the lexicographic product of the destination
prefix ordering by the source prefix ordering.)</t>

<t>In practice, this means that a source-specific Babel implementation
must take care that any lower layer that performs packet forwarding obey
this semantics.  More precisely:</t>

<t><list style="symbols">
<t>if the lower layers implement the destination-first ordering, then the
Babel implementation SHOULD use them directly;</t>
<t>if the lower layers can hold source-specific routes, but not with the
right semantics, then the Babel implementation MUST either silently ignore
any source-specific routes, or disambiguate the routing table by using
a suitable disambiguation algorithm (see Section V.B of
<xref target="SS-ROUTING"/> for such an algorithm);</t>
<t>if the lower layers cannot hold source-specific routes, then a Babel
implementation MUST silently ignore any source-specific routes.</t>
</list></t>

</section>

<section title="Protocol Operation">

<t>This extension does not fundamentally change the operation of the Babel
protocol, and we therefore only describe differences between the original
protocol and the extended protocol.</t>

<t>In the original protocol, three TLVs carry a destination prefix:
Updates, Route Requests and Seqno Requests.  This specification extends
these messages so that they may carry a Source Prefix sub-TLV, as
described in <xref target="protocol-encoding"/> below.  The sub-TLV is
marked as mandatory, so that an unextended implementation will silently
ignore the whole enclosing TLV.  A node obeying this specification MUST
NOT send a TLV with a zero-length source prefix: instead, it sends a TLV
with no Source Prefix sub-TLV.  Conversely, an extended implementation
MUST interpret an unextended TLV as carrying a source prefix of zero
length.  Taken together, these properties ensure interoperability between
the original and extended protocols (see <xref target="compatibility"/>
below).</t>

<section title="Protocol Messages">

<t>This extension allows three TLVs of the original Babel protocol to
carry a source prefix: Update TLVs, Route Request TLVs and Seqno Request
TLVs.</t>

<t>In order to advertise a route with a non-zero length source prefix,
a node sends a source-specific Update, i.e., an Update with a Source
Prefix sub-TLV.  When a node receives a source-specific Update (prefix,
source prefix, router-id, seqno, metric) from a neighbour neigh, it
behaves as described in <xref target="RFC8966"/> Section&nbsp;3.5.4, except
that the entry under consideration is indexed by (prefix, source prefix,
neigh) rather than just (prefix, neigh).</t>

<t>Similarly, when a node needs to send a Request of either kind that
applies to a route with a non-zero length source prefix, it sends
a source-specific Request, i.e., a Request with a Source Prefix sub-TLV.
When a node receives a source-specific Request, it behaves as described in
Section 3.8 of <xref target="RFC8966"/>, except that the request applies to
the Route Table entry carrying the source prefix indicated by the
Source Prefix sub-TLV.</t>

</section>

<section title="Wildcard Messages">

<t>In the original protocol, the Address Encoding value 0 is used for
wildcard messages: messages that apply to all routes, of any address
family and with any destination prefix.  Wildcard messages are allowed
in two places in the protocol: wildcard retractions are used to retract
all of the routes previously advertised by a node on a given interface,
and wildcard Route Requests are used to request a full dump of the Route
Table from a given node.  Wildcard messages are intended to apply to all
routes, including routes decorated with additional data and AE values to
be defined by future extensions, and hence this specification extends
wildcard operations to apply to all routes, whatever the value of the
source prefix.</t>

<t>More precisely, a node receiving an Update with the AE field set to
0 and the Metric field set to infinity (a wildcard retraction) MUST apply
the route acquisition procedure described in Section 3.5.4 of <xref
target="RFC8966"/> to all of the routes that it has learned from the sending
node, whatever the value of the source prefix.  A node MUST NOT send
a wildcard retraction with an attached source prefix, and a node that
receives a wildcard retraction with a source prefix MUST ignore the
retraction.</t>

<t>Similarly, a node that receives a route request with the AE field set
to 0 (a wildcard route request) SHOULD send a full routing table dump,
including routes with a non-zero length source prefix.  A node MUST NOT
send a wildcard request that carries a source prefix, and a node receiving
a wildcard request with a source prefix MUST ignore it.</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="Compatibility with the base protocol" anchor="compatibility">

<t>The protocol extension defined in this document is, to a great extent,
interoperable with the base protocol defined in <xref target="RFC8966"/>
(and all previously standardised extensions).  More precisely, if
non-source-specific routers and source-specific routers are mixed in
a single routing domain, Babel's loop-avoidance properties are preserved,
and, in particular, no persistent routing loops will occur.</t>

<t>However, this extension is encoded using mandatory sub-TLVs, introduced in
<xref target="RFC8966"/>, and therefore is not compatible with the older version
of the Babel Routing Protocol <xref target="RFC6126"/> which does not support
such sub-TLVs.  Consequently, this extension MUST NOT be used with routers
implementing RFC 6126, otherwise persistent routing loops may occur.</t>

<section title="Loop-avoidance" anchor="loop">

<t>The extension defined in this protocol uses a new Mandatory sub-TLV to
carry the source prefix information.  As discussed in Section&nbsp;4.4 of
<xref target="RFC8966"/>, this encoding ensures that non-source-specific
routers will silently ignore the whole TLV, which is necessary to avoid
persistent routing loops in hybrid networks.</t>

<t>Consider two nodes A and B, with A source-specific announcing a route
to (D,&nbsp;S).  Suppose that B (non-source-specific) merely ignores the
source prefix information when it receives the update rather than ignoring
the whole TLV, and re-announces the route as D.  This re-announcement
reaches A, which treats it as (D,&nbsp;::/0).  Packets destined to D but
not sourced in S will be forwarded by A to B, and by B to A, causing a
persistent routing loop:</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
    (D,S)                 (D)
     <--                 <--
  ------ A ----------------- B
           -->
          (D,::/0)
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>

<section title="Starvation and Blackholes">

<t>In general, the discarding of source-specific routes by
non-source-specific routers will cause route starvation.  Intuitively,
unless there are enough non-source-specific routes in the network,
non-source-specific routers will suffer starvation, and discard packets
for destinations that are only announced by source-specific routers.</t>

<t>A simple yet sufficient condition for avoiding starvation is to build a
connected source-specific backbone that includes all of the edge routers,
and announce a (non-source-specific) default route towards the
backbone.</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="Protocol Encoding" anchor="protocol-encoding">

<t>This extension defines a new sub-TLV used to carry a source prefix: the
Source Prefix sub-TLV.  It can be used within an Update, a Route Request
or a Seqno Request TLV to match a source-specific entry of the Route
Table, in conjunction with the destination prefix natively carried by
these TLVs.</t>

<t>Since a source-specific routing entry is characterized by a single
destination prefix and a single source prefix, a source-specific message
contains exactly one Source Prefix sub-TLV.  A node MUST NOT send more
than one Source Prefix sub-TLV in a TLV, and a node receiving more than
one Source Prefix sub-TLV in a single TLV MUST ignore this TLV.  It MAY
ignore the whole packet.</t>

<section title="Source Prefix sub-TLV">
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Type = 128  |    Length     |  Source Plen  | Source Prefix...
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Fields:
<list style="hanging" hangIndent="10">
<t hangText="Type">Set to 128 to indicate a Source Prefix
sub-TLV.</t>
<t hangText="Length">The length of the body, in octets, exclusive of the
Type and Length fields.</t>
<t hangText="Source Plen">The length of the advertised source prefix, in
bits.  This MUST NOT be 0.</t>
<t hangText="Source Prefix">The source prefix being advertised.  This
field's size is (Source Plen)/8 octets rounded upwards.</t>
</list>
</t>

<t>The contents of the Source Prefix sub-TLV are interpreted according to
the AE of the enclosing TLV.  If a TLV with AE equal to 0 contains
a Source Prefix sub-TLV, then the whole TLV MUST be ignored.  Similarly,
if a TLV contains multiple Source Prefix sub-TLVs, then the whole TLV MUST
be ignored.</t>

<t>Note that this sub-TLV is a mandatory sub-TLV.  Therefore, as described
in Section 4.4 of <xref target="RFC8966"/>, the whole TLV MUST be ignored if
that sub-TLV is not understood (or malformed).  Otherwise, routing loops
may occur (see <xref target="loop"/>).</t>

</section>

<section title="Source-specific Update">

<t>The source-specific Update is an Update TLV with a Source Prefix
sub-TLV.  It advertises or retracts source-specific routes in the same
manner as routes with non-source-specific Updates (see <xref
target="RFC8966"/>).  A wildcard retraction (Update with AE equal to 0) MUST
NOT carry a Source Prefix sub-TLV.</t>

<t>Babel uses a stateful compression scheme to reduce the size taken by
destination prefixes in update TLVs (see Section 4.5 of <xref
target="RFC8966"/>).  The source prefix defined by this extension is not
compressed.  On the other hand, compression is allowed for the destination
prefixes carried by source-specific updates.  As described in Section 4.5
of <xref target="RFC8966"/>, unextended implementations will correctly
update their parser state while otherwise ignoring the whole TLV.</t>

</section>

<section title="Source-specific (Route) Request" anchor="ss-request">

<t>A source-specific Route Request is a Route Request TLV with a Source
Prefix sub-TLV.  It prompts the receiver to send an update for a given
pair of destination and source prefixes, as described in Section 3.8.1.1
of <xref target="RFC8966"/>.  A wildcard request (Route Request with AE
equals to 0) MUST NOT carry a Source Prefix sub-TLV; if a wildcard request
with a Source Prefix sub-TLV is received, then the request MUST be
ignored.</t>

</section>

<section title="Source-Specific Seqno Request">

<t>A source-specific Seqno Request is a Seqno Request TLV with a Source
Prefix sub-TLV.  It requests the receiving node to perform the procedure
described in Section 3.8.1.2 of <xref target="RFC8966"/>, but applied to
a pair of a destination and source prefix.</t>

</section>

</section>

<section title="IANA Considerations">

<t>IANA has allocated sub-TLV number 128 for the Source Prefix sub-TLV in
the Babel sub-TLV types registry.</t>

</section>

<section title="Security considerations">

<t>The extension defined in this document adds a new sub-TLV to three TLVs
already present in the original Babel protocol, and does not change the
security properties of the protocol itself.  However, the additional
flexibility provided by source-specific routing might invalidate the
assumptions made by some network administrators, which could conceivably
lead to security issues.</t>

<t>For example, a network administrator might be tempted to abuse route
filtering (Appendix C of <xref target="RFC8966"/>) as a security mechanism.
Unless the filtering rules are designed to take source-specific routing
into account, they might be bypassed by a source-specific route, which
might cause traffic to reach a portion of a network that was thought to be
protected.  Similarly, a network administrator might assume that no route
is more specific than a host route, and use a host route in order to
direct traffic for a given destination through a security device (e.g.,
a firewall); source-specific routing invalidates this assumption, and in
some topologies announcing a source-specific route might conceivably be
used to bypass the security device.</t>

</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">

<t>The authors are grateful to Donald Eastlake and Joel Halpern for their
help with this document.</t>
    
</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references title="Normative References">

<reference anchor="RFC2119"><front>
<title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
<author fullname="Scott Bradner" initials="S." surname="Bradner"/>
<date month="March" year="1997"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2119"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="BCP84"><front>
<title>Ingress Filtering for Multihomed Networks</title>
<author fullname="Fred Baker" initials="F." surname="Baker"/>
<author fullname="Pekka Savola" initials="P." surname="Savola"/>
<date month="March" year="2004"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="84"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3704"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC8966" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8966">
<front>
<title>The Babel Routing Protocol</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Chroboczek" fullname="J. Chroboczek"/>
<author initials="D." surname="Schinazi" fullname="D. Schinazi"/>
<date year="2021" month="January"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8966"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8966"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="RFC8174"><front>
<title>Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC 2119 Key Words</title>
<author initials="B." surname="Leiba" fullname="B. Leiba"/>
<date year="2017" month="May"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8174"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8174"/>
</reference>

</references>

<references title="Informative References">

<reference anchor="RFC6126" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc6126">
<front>
<title>The Babel Routing Protocol</title>
<author initials="J." surname="Chroboczek" fullname="J. Chroboczek"/>
<date year="2011" month="April"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6126"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC6126"/>
</reference>

<reference anchor="SS-ROUTING">
<front>
<title>Source-Specific Routing</title>
<author initials="M." surname="Boutier" fullname="Matthieu Boutier"/>
<author initials="J." surname="Chroboczek" fullname="Juliusz Chroboczek"/>
<date year="2014" month="August"/>
</front>
<annotation>In Proc. IFIP Networking 2015.  A slightly earlier version
is available online from http://arxiv.org/pdf/1403.0445.</annotation>
</reference>

</references>

</back>

</rfc>

